<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="chrome://liberator/content/help.xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM "chrome://liberator/content/liberator.dtd">

<document
    name="developer"
    title="&liberator.appname; Developer information"
    xmlns="http://vimperator.org/namespaces/liberator"
    xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<h1 tag="developer-information">Developer information</h1>
<toc start="2"/>

<h2 tag="writing-docs documentation">Writing documentation</h2>

<p>
    For every new feature, writing documentation is <em>mandatory</em> for the
    patch to be accepted. The docs are written in an XML dialect similar to
    XHTML, with a few tags specific to our documentation. For example:
</p>

<code><![CDATA[
<item>
    <tags><![CDATA[<F1> :help :h help]]]]><![CDATA[></tags>
    <spec>:h<oa>elp</oa> <a>subject</a></spec>
    <spec><![CDATA[<F1>]]]]><![CDATA[></spec>
    <description>
        <p>
            Open help window.
            The default section is shown unless <a>subject</a> is specified.
            If you need help for a specific topic, try <ex>:help overview</ex>.
        </p>
    </description>
</item>
]]></code>

<p>
    creates a new help section for the command <ex>:help</ex> and for
    the related key binding, <k name="F1"/>. It also creates help tags
    for the command, its shortcuts, the key binding, and the general
    topic, 'help'. These tags enable linking to this section when from
    other mentions of the topic and from the <ex>:help</ex> command.
    The above code displays as:
</p>

<html:div style="margin: 2em;">
<item>
    <tags><![CDATA[<F1> :help :h help]]></tags>
    <spec>:h<oa>elp</oa> <a>subject</a></spec>
    <spec><![CDATA[<F1>]]></spec>
    <description>
        <p>
            Open help window.
            The default section is shown unless <a>subject</a> is specified.
            If you need help for a specific topic, try <ex>:help overview</ex>.
        </p>
    </description>
</item>
</html:div>

<p>
    If you don't know in which file/section you should put some
    documentation, ask on the mailing list or on
    <link topic="irc://irc.freenode.net/vimperator">#vimperator</link>.
</p>

<h2 tag="generating-docs">Generating documentation</h2>

<p>
    You can also autogenerate most of the XML help after you have
    written a new command, mapping or option.
</p>

<example><ex>:echo util.generateHelp(commands.get(<str>addons</str>), <![CDATA[<p>Extra text</p>]]>)</ex></example>

<h2 tag="writing-plugins">Writing plugins</h2>

<p>
    Writing &liberator.appname; plugins is incredibly simple.
    Plugins are simply JavaScript files which run with full chrome
    privileges and have full access to the &liberator.appname; and
    &liberator.host; APIs. Each plugin has its own global object,
    which means that the variables and functions that you create
    won't pollute the global <em>window</em> or private
    <em>liberator</em> namespaces. This means that there's no need
    to wrap your plugin in a closure, as is often the practice in
    JavaScript development. Furthermore, any plugin which is
    installed in your <o>runtimepath</o><em>/plugin</em> directory
    will find its context stored in
    <em>plugins.&lt;pluginName></em>, which is often invaluable
    during development and testing.
</p>

<h3 tag="plugin-documentation">Plugin documentation</h3>

<p>
    Plugins may provide inline documentation, which will appear on
    the <ex>:help plugins</ex> page. The markup for help entries
    is the same as the above, with a few more plugin specific
    entries. Here is an example from the popular
    <em>flashblock</em> extension:
</p>

<code><![CDATA[
var INFO = 
<plugin name="flashblock" version="1.0"
        href="http://ticket.vimperator.org/9"
        summary="Flash Blocker"
        xmlns="http://vimperator.org/namespaces/liberator">
    <author email="maglione.k@gmail.com">Kris Maglione</author>
    <license href="http://opensource.org/licenses/mit-license.php">MIT</license>
    <project name="Vimperator" minVersion="2.0"/>
    <p>
        This plugin provides the same features as the ever popular FlashBlock
        Firefox addon. Flash animations are substituted with place holders which
        play the original animation when clicked. Additionally, this plugin provides
        options to control which sites can play animations without restrictions, and
        triggers to toggle the playing of animation on the current page.
	commandline from the data in a given form.
    </p>
    <item>
	<tags>'flashblock' 'fb'</tags>
	<spec>'flashblock' 'fb'</spec>
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default>true</default>
	<description>
            <p>
                Controls the blocking of flash animations. When true, place
                holders are substituted for flash animations on untrusted sites.
            </p>
	</description>
    </item>]]>
    <em>…</em><![CDATA[
</plugin>;
]]>
</code>

<p>
    The inline XML is made possible by
    <link topic="https://developer.mozilla.org/en/E4X">E4X</link>.
    It's important that the documentation be assigned to the
    <em>INFO</em> variable, or &liberator.appname; will not be able
    to find it. The documentation that you provide behaves exactly
    as other &liberator.appname; documentation, which means that
    the tags you provide are available via <ex>:help</ex> with
    full tag completion and cross-referencing support. Although
    documentation is not required, we strongly recommend that all
    plugin authors provide at least basic documentation of the
    functionality of their plugins and of each of the options,
    commands, and especially mappings that they provide.
</p>

</document>

<!-- vim:se sts=4 sw=4 et: -->
